# **ASIF IQBAL RAHAMAN**

 □ asif256000+job@gmail.com https://linkedin.com/in/asif-iqbal-r/ https://github.com/asif256000/

 Blacksburg, VA, USA https://asifiqbal.xvz/

As a Computer Science Graduate with 3+ years of industry experience and a year in academic research, I am actively seeking full-time role from June 2024. My experience in diverse domains position me well to contribute to innovative and challenging projects.

#### SKILLS

Python, Rust, Javascript, SQL, Bash, Shell Script, HTML, CSS, C++, Java, GoLang, VueJS Programming:

Frameworks: Flask, FastAPI, RestAPI, Pandas, Numpy, AWS-CDK, PyTorch, Win32, PyautoGUI, Matplotlib, JSON, OpenCV, Django, Pillow Tools: Git, Jenkins, Docker, Unix, Linux, MacOS Terminal, Nginx, Supervisor, MySQL, MongoDB, AWS, Selenium, Airflow, Azure

# **EDUCATION**

VIRGINIA TECH - BLACKSBURG, US

Aug 2022 - May 2024 (Exp)

Master of Engineering in Computer Science

CGPA: 3.9/4.0

Courses: Al Tools for Software Delivery, Natural Language Processing, Data Analysis, Applications of Machine Learning, Computer Vision

VIT UNIVERSITY - VELLORE. IN

Aug 2015 - May 2019

**Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science** 

CGPA: 8.0/10.0

Courses: Data Structures & Algorithms, Database Management, Software Development, Data Mining, Cyber Security, Network Architecture

# **EXPERIENCE**

#### DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTATIONAL CELL BIOLOGY, VIRGINIA TECH - BLACKSBURG, US Software Developer

Oct 2022 - Present

- Designed an automated simulation of cell cycle with boolean model of protein interactions with significantly better efficiency and accuracy.
- Utilized Pandas, Numpy for data manipulation, database APIs for data validation and dataclass to structure inputs in Python for the project.
- Achieved a **5x increase** in simulation speed for model perturbation analysis by implementing parallel processing and algorithm optimization on the ARC@VT supercomputer for automated improvement of exponentially growing (approx 1.6M interactions) cell interaction models.
- Resulted in a research publication available at biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.10.30.564745v1 under review of PLOS One journal.

#### SECLORE TECHNOLOGIES PVT. LTD. - MUMBAI. IN **Product Engineer**

Dec 2021 - Jul 2022

- Significantly reduced customer onboarding from several days to few hours, enhanced operational efficiency by automating DevOps with AWS-CDK and developed a cloud-based deployment solution leveraging AWS CloudFormation, ECS, DynamoDB, and CloudWatch.
- Optimized deployment by designing scalable infrastructure as code with Docker and Jenkins for containerization and pipeline execution.
- Fostered teamwork and agile development, delivering the initial framework in 4 months utilizing CI/CD principles in a team of 3.

#### ERICSSON INDIA GLOBAL SERVICES PVT. LTD. - BANGALORE, IN Software Engineer

Jan 2019 - Jul 2021

- Developed a rule-based recommendation engine using Pandas and Numpy for network performance analysis, achieving a 36% automation gain for international telecom clients through enhanced data processing and analysis, and optimizing with parallel computing.
- Constructed an automated API system for daily processing of ~30GB data from datalakes, improving data handling efficiency by cleaning. categorizing, and storing data as parguet files using Pandas and requests library, facilitating faster access for the recommendation engine.
- Engineered an RPA framework to streamline network management operations, securing 35% boost in automation efficiency by utilizing OpenCV, Selenium, win32 for targeted actions, NoSQL and MySQL for data integration, with backend developed using Rest API.
- Integrated the RPA framework with Ericsson's BotStore platform using internal APIs, streamlining the automation process.

#### **PROJECTS**

## Personal Website with FastAPI, AWS and Nginx

Jan 2024

- Embraced hands-on learning approach by designing a dynamic website using FastAPI, SQLAlchemy, Jinja2 in Python, PyTest for testing automation, docker-compose for containerization of the application and deployed in AWS EC2 with Nginx proxy server for efficient routing.
- Designed the website with a forward-thinking structure to potentially support multiple user profiles, enhancing scalability and engagement.

## **EEG Signal to Text Extraction**

Nov 2023

- Replicated the pioneering research of Wang, Ji et al to convert EEG signal to text tokens by fine-tuning BART model with custom data.
- Implemented zero-shot algorithm using PyTorch to classify the generated texts for verifying sentiment analysis of EEG signals.

# Multiple Object Tracking using FairMOT and GAN

**Dec 2023** 

- Constructed a novel architecture for multiple object tracking, integrating FairMOT with Generative Adversarial Networks (GAN).
- Demonstrated that isolating the generator in a separate layer in the architecture diminishes the tracking performance, as the discriminator readily distinguishes between fake and real data based on layer origin, highlighting the importance of architecture design.

#### Football (Soccer) Commentary Generation with Fine-Tuned GPT Model

Ongoing

- Enhancing artificial intelligence generated commentary realism by fine-tuning GPT model with real-game data through prompt engineering.
- Leveraging a text-to-speech and translation API to emulate Peter Drury's voice for multilingual commentary and enhanced accessibility.

# **CERTIFICATIONS & AWARDS**

Python for Data Science and Machine Learning Bootcamp

Udemy Certificate - May 2021

Improving Deep Network: Hyperparameter Tuning, Regularization & Optimization

Coursera Certificate - Jul 2020

**Neural Networks and Deep Learning** 

Coursera Certificate - Jan 2020

Bi-annual Galactic Award from Ericsson (2020) for achieving outstanding business excellence with data automation framework.